D.C. Statehood Movement Leaders Oral History Project OHP020
People's Archive, MLK Library
D.C. Statehood Movement Leaders Oral History Project
1997-1999
People's Archive, MLK Library
District of Columbia. Public Library
OHP020
2 Linear feet
2 Boxes
Arrangement
Series 1: Transcripts Materials in this series include transcripts for all interviews. There are no transcripts for the "Statehood Forum." Series 2: Interviews Materials in this series include master copies of the oral histories on audio cassette. There are duplicate copies of all audio recordings except two tapes of 20-07 and all of 20-11.
Biographical / Historical
The D.C. Public Library was founded in 1896 by an act of Congress "to furnish books and other printed matter and information service convenient to the homes and offices of all residents of the District."
Custodial History
The DC Public Library conducted these interviews and panel discussion between 1997 and 1999. Tapes and transcripts were officially transferred to the Washingtoniana Division shortly after their completion. There is no transfer documentation between Library departments.
Related Materials
Julius Hobson, 001 Home Rule Oral History, OHP018 Home Rule Committee Collection 055 League of Women Voters of the District of Columbia 033 Self-Determination for DC Collection 003
Scope and Contents
Between 1997 and 1999 the D.C. Public Library and Councilmember Hilda Mason's office jointly sponsored a program to conduct oral histories of D.C. Statehood movement leaders. The project was funded by a grant from the D.C. Humanities Council and documents the experiences of 10 important Statehood movement leaders. The interviews cover such topics as memories of activist Julius Hobson, the early founding of the Statehood Party, local politics and referendums, constitutional convention, and the defeat of the statehood legislation. After the completion of the project the Library held a Statehood Forum at the Library and an audio recording of that event is also included with this collection.
Oral History; Statehood (American politics); Politics and government
- Series 1: Transcripts
  Scope and Contents
  Materials in this series include transcripts for all interviews. There are no transcripts for the "Statehood Forum."
  - Lou Aronica, 1998 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Charles Mason, 1998 December 7 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hilda Mason, 1998 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Charles and Hilda Mason, 1998 July 9 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chauncey and Sandra Thomas, 1999 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Edward Guinan, 1998 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sam Smith, 1998 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Deborah Hanrahan, 1998 December 29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chuck Stone, 1999 April 11 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Tina Hobson, 1999 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series 2: Interviews
  Materials in this series include master copies of the oral histories on audio cassette. There are duplicate copies of all audio recordings except two tapes of 20-07 and all of 20-11.
  - Lou Aronica, 1998 October 6 (Box 2, Tape 20-01)
  - Lou Aronica, 1998 October 6 (Box 2, Tape 20-01)
  - Lou Aronica, 1998 October 6 (Box 2, Tape 20-01)
  - Charles Mason, 1998 December 7 (Box 2, Tape 20-02)
  - Charles Mason, 1998 December 7 (Box 2, Tape 20-02)
  - Hilda Mason, 1998 June 1 (Box 2, Tape 20-03)
  - Charles and Hilda Mason, 1998 July 9 (Box 2, Tape 20-04)
  - Chauncey and Sandra Thomas, 1999 January 6 (Box 2, Tape 20-05)
  - Chauncey and Sandra Thomas, 1999 January 6 (Box 2, Tape 20-05)
  - Edward Guinan, 1998 December 15 (Box 2, Tape 20-06)
  - Sam Smith, 1998 November 18 (Box 2, Tape 20-07)
  - Sam Smith, 1998 November 18 (Box 2, Tape 20-07)
  - Sam Smith, 1998 November 18 (Box 2, Tape 20-07)
  - Deborah Hanrahan, 1998 December 29 (Box 2, Tape 20-08)
  - Deborah Hanrahan, 1998 December 29 (Box 2, Tape 20-08)
  - Chuck Stone, 1999 April 11 (Box 2, Tape 20-09)
  - Tina Hobson, 1999 April 23 (Box 2, Tape 20-10)
  - Tina Hobson, 1999 April 23 (Box 2, Tape 20-10)
  - Statehood Forum, 1999 March 6 (Box 2, Tape 20-11)
  - Statehood Forum, 1999 March 6 (Box 2, Tape 20-11)